To make our project work and servable by the dev server or later in production, we need to connect
Projemizi dev sunucusu tarafndan veya daha sonra retime hazr hale
our index.html file to the output files which are generated, when using the dev server they are only stored
getirmek iin dizinimizi balamalyz. html dosyas oluturulan kt dosyalarna, dev sunucuyu kullanrken
in memory but they're still generated. We need to install a webpack plugin for that,
sadece bellekte saklanrlar ancak yine de retilirler. Bunun iin bir webpack eklentisi
with npm install --save-, save dev, excuse me a lot of dashes, with save-dev, we can
yklemeliyiz, npm install --save-, kaydet dev, bana bir sr tire, kaydet-dev ile,
install the html-webpack-plugin,
html-webpack-plugin'i kurabiliriz, bu zel bir eklentidir. html dosyamz kmza
this is a special plugin which allows to connect our html file with our output and webpack will do that
ve web paketimize balamak iin bunu otomatik olarak yapar ve birlikte verilen komut dosyasn
automatically and inject our bundled script and so on into that html file. In the webpack
ve bu html dosyasna enjekte eder. Webpack yaplandrmasnda, imdi eklentileri ekliyoruz, kk
config, we now add plugins,
yaplandrma seviyesinde yeni bir dm
it's a new node on the root config level, plugins and it takes an array as an argument or as a value, I should
var, eklentiler ve bir argman veya bir deer olarak bir dizi almalym,
say.
demeliyim.
And now first of all we need to install or import
Ve imdi ilk biz html
I should say the html webpack plugin, so I'll create a constant which I'll name
webpack eklentisi sylemeliyim ya da ithal etmeliyiz, bu
htmlWebpackPlugin but the name is up to you
yzden htmlWebpackPlugin ismini vereceim bir sabit oluturacam
and here I will require html-webpack-plugin, the package we just installed.
ama adnz size kalm ve burada html-webpack-plugin gerektirecektir, yeni yklediimiz paket.
Now in the plugins array,
imdi eklenti dizisinde,
I create a new instance of it, new HtmlWebpackPlugin and we pass an object to the constructor where
yeni bir HTMLmlWebpackPlugin rnei yaratyorum ve bu eklentiyi yaplandrdmz kurucuya bir nesne
we configure this plugin. Here,
gnderiyoruz. Burada bir
I'll setup a template, so the html file I want to use as a basis and there of course, I want to use
ablon kuracam, bu yzden bir temel olarak kullanmak istediim html dosyas
my html file in the source folder. So I will point to it with dirname and then I'll simply add
ve tabii ki html dosyasn kaynak klasrde kullanmak istiyorum. Bu yzden dirname ile gstereceim ve sonra / source /
/source/index.html,
index ekleyeceim. html, ona
constructing a path to it.
bir yol ina etmek.
So now we're pointing to the file we want to use as a template,
Yani imdi ablon olarak kullanmak istediimiz dosyaya iaret
I want to inject my stuff into the body that's extra configuration we can pass to the plugin here and
ediyoruz, ekstra yaplandrma yapabildiim gvdeye eyalarm enjekte etmek istiyorum ki buraya eklentiyi ve kt dosyasna aktarabiliriz,
the output file, filename should also be index.html,
dosya ad da dizin olmal. html, sonuta retecei dosya,
that's the file it will eventually generate, again for the server
sadece sunucuda bellek iin, daha sonra bunu
only in memory,
retmek iin
later when we use a different workflow for building this, for production, it will give us the real files we
farkl bir i ak kullandmzda, retim iin, bize bir sunucuya ykleyebileceimiz
could upload to a server.
gerek dosyalar verecektir.
So with that added, let's now restart npm start,
Yani ekledik, imdi npm start
now we should get the connection from webpack to the html file,
balayalm, imdi webpack'den html dosyasna balanty almalyz,
so let's see if that then works. Let's revisit localhost8080 and we do see an empty page
o zaman ie yarayp yaramadn grelim. Localhost8080'i tekrar ziyaret edelim ve en azndan bo
now at least, we get some errors there though.
bir sayfa gryoruz, ancak baz hatalar var.
Now these are react errors which is a good sign,
imdi bunlar iyi bir iaret
our application seems to run, it's informing us that we likely forgot to export our component from the
olan tepki hatalardr, uygulamamzn alt grlyor, bize bileenimizi tanmlad dosyadan da aktarmay
file it's defined in. Let's check,
unuttuumuzu bildiriyor. Kontrol edelim, pizzaImage'i,
we're exporting the pizzaImage, the pizza class based component and the user component but we never exported
pizza snf bileenini ve kullanc bileenini da aktaryoruz ancak uygulamay asla ihra etmedik, bu yzden uygulama
the app,
bileenine
so let's add a default export to the app component,
varsaylan bir ihracat ekleyelim, bu her zaman bir ey
that's always the danger in building something
oluturmada tehlike oluturuyor ve imdi
and now this looks much better,
bu daha iyi
we see the users and now it becomes interesting, that's the pizza. We see the pizza and awesome is if we inspect
grnyor Kullanclar gryoruz ve imdi ilgin oluyor, bu pizza. Biz pizza grmek ve a sekmesini incelemek mthi
the network tab and I go back to users and reload the app, watch the network requests,
ve ben kullanclara geri gitmek ve uygulamay yeniden yklemek, a isteklerini izlemek, 0
you see that 0.js file?
olduunu gryoruz. js dosyas m?
That's our lazy loaded javascript file we downloaded, so lazy loading is working here and our react
Bizim indirdiimiz tembel ykl javascript dosyas, bu yzden tembel ykleme burada alyor ve
application is working,
bizim tepki uygulama
the styling also seems to kick in, if we inspect the pizza image
alyor, stil ayn zamanda tekme gibi grnyor,
we see we're using css modules here and we get the styles we setup in our css files.
biz pizza grntsn incelediimizde burada css modllerini kullanyoruz ve stilleri alyoruz css dosyalarmzda kurulum yapyoruz.
Now all I'll do here is a quick and easy fix here on the links,
imdi burada yapacam her ey balantlar zerinde hzl ve kolay
I don't like the fact that we don't have a whitespace in front of the second link, let's fix it like that
bir zm, ikinci balantnn nnde bir boluk bulunmad gereini beenmedim, hadi bunun gibi dzeltelim ama
but that's purely cosmetic.
bu tamamen kozmetik.
What's important to us is we have a working workflow, a working project setup where we can create
Bizim iin nemli olan, alan bir i akmz, bu derste rendiiniz zelliklere sahip
a react app with the features you learned about in this course.
bir tepki uygulamas oluturabileceimiz bir alma projesi kurulumumuz.
Now that's only the development workflow, the development server,
imdi sadece gelitirme i ak, gelitirme sunucusu, eer
if we now want to ship this app to a real server, we'll have to do some adjustments to the setup to
imdi bu uygulamay gerek bir sunucuya gndermek istiyorsak, hazrlanmak ve retim iin optimize
have it prepared and to have it be optimized for production.
edilmek zere kurulum iin baz ayarlamalar yapmamz gerekecek.